Marilynn Gelfman Karp Collection of Ephemera PR 279
New-York Historical Society
- Series XV. Sheet Music, 1842-1948
  The sheet music found in this collection spans over a century, from 1842-1948. Today, sheet music is a particularly valuable form of ephemera, with its text and pictorial covers offering keen insight into contemporary pastimes and the societal and racial attitudes of their eras. In the 1840s, such pictorial covers were characterized by simple black and white designs often incorporating ornamental scrollwork and simple lettering, and were commonly reproduced with woodcuts, steel engraving, and lithography. Advances in color printing technology (chromolithography) by the end of the 19th century brought about an increased focus on illustrated covers, which became a successful vehicle for commercial artists. As the Industrial Revolution gave rise to prosperity and the growth of the middle classes, Americans found themselves with increased time for leisure activities, which included the home piano as a popular form of entertainment. In America, the production and popularity of sheet music would reach its heyday in the late 19th century, with the rise of Tin Pan Alley and the American music publishing industry. Over the ensuing decades, demand for sheet music would gradually lessen in importance with the introduction of the phonograph and radio, and the advent of the record industry.
  The thematic groups in the series list below were previously arranged by the collector, with category titles assigned by N-YHS. The remaining sheet music in the collection has been arranged by decade.
  - New York, 1896-1935 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 171)
  - African-American, 1860-1918 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 172)
  - Patriotic, 1898-1941 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 173)
  - Patriotic, 1898-1941 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 174)
  - Patriotic, 1898-1941 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 175)
  - Patriotic, 1898-1941 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 176)
  - Various subjects, 1800s (Offsite-box 15, Folder 177)
  - Various subjects, 1900-1909 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 178)
  - Various subjects, 1900-1909 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 179)
  - Various subjects, 1900-1909 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 180)
  - Various subjects, 1900-1909 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 181)
  - Various subjects, 1900-1909 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 182)
  - Various subjects, 1900-1909 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 183)
  - Various subjects, 1900-1909 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 184)
  - Various subjects, 1910-1919 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 185)
  - Various subjects, 1910-1919 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 186)
  - Various subjects, 1910-1919 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 187)
  - Various subjects, 1910-1919 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 188)
  - Various subjects, 1921-1925 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 189)
  - Various subjects, 1926-1929 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 190)
  - Various subjects, 1932-1934 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 191)
  - Various subjects, 1935-1939 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 192)
  - Various subjects, 1940-1948 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 193)
- Series XVI. Photography, circa 1880s-1945
  World War II Ephemera (various formats)
  Historic note
  Postmortem Photography: More than any other form of pictorial representation, photography is inextricably tied to remembrance and its invention forever changed the way we relate with and document our world. Following closely on the heels of photography's introduction was the practice of postmortem photography, which, after 1841, spread across America becoming prevalent in both urban and rural areas, and remained culturally embraced well into the early 20th century. From 1840-1880, the majority of postmortem images were taken within the private home, where the body was posed naturalistically. While sometimes depicted as if alive and awake, very often the deceased were shown as if to be sleeping peacefully rather than dead, an illusion that gently denies death, while at the same time serving to beautify, soften, and romanticize it. By the latter 19th century, with the rise of the funeral and embalming industries, straightforward full length "casket photographs" became very popular, focusing less on the individual, and more on the social aspect of the funeral event or funeral parlor setting (where the corpse was often upstaged by profuse floral arrangements).
  Today these images serve as culturally bound artifacts that provide a trace of the sociocultural importance that such image making had for their producers and users. Photographs of a deceased loved one functioned as icons, substitutes, and reminders of loss. Most importantly, they captured memory by recording for posterity a lasting image of the deceased.
  Salamagundi Club, NYC, May 5, 1945: Mounted black and white photograph of the 75th Anniversary Special Exhibition Dinner of the Salamagundi Club, which includes 55 well-known New York artists and their works hanging on the background walls. The Salamagundi Club (also known as the Salamagundi Art Club) was founded in 1871 and still remains active today with (as of 2009) over 800 members.
  Gansevoort and West Washington Markets, NYC, 1903: Embossed, mounted black and white photograph of the Gansevoort and West Washington Markets, showing a multitude of vendors, wagons, goods, and commercial oyster bars.
  - NYC: Salamagundi Club, 1945 (Oversize Flat File, Folder 194)
  - NYC: Gansevoort and West Washington Markets, 1903 (Oversize Flat File, Folder 194)
  - Postmortem Photographs, circa 1880-1920 (Oversize Flat File, Folder 195)
- Series XVII. Prints and Drawings, 1930
  - New York Post Cartoon by Clarence Batchelor (3-color final drawing), 1930 (Oversize Flat File, Folder 196)
- Series XVIII. Miscellaneous publications relating to New York City (Offsite-box 16)
  - Magazine- New York Latest Collections: spring and summer 1927 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 194)
  - Interborough Rapid Transit: The Subway in New York (Offsite-box 16, Folder 195)
- Series XIX. Ivan Karp- OK Harris
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of a range of flyers and advertisment postcards outlining upcoming exhibitions at OK Harris, and a variety of prints and posters exhibited at O.K. Harris from the establishment of the gallery in 1969 to its close in 2014.
  - Subseries XIX.1 OK Harris flyers
    - OK Harris flyers, 1970-1974 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 170.A)
    - OK Harris exhibition flyers, 1975-1979 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 170.B)
    - OK Harris flyers, 1986, 1988, 1989 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 170.C)
  - Subseries XIX.2 OK Harris advertisement postcards
    Arrangement
    The dates of these advertisement postcards range from 1969, when OK Harris was founded, until its close in 2014. These files have been arranged chronologically and are separated by dividers. As a result of the requirements, some files have been removed from box 17 and are stored in document sized folders held box 13.
    - OK Harris Advertisement Postcards, 1969-2014 (Offsite-box 20, Box 17)
    - OK Harris Advertisement Postcards, 1969-1973 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 170.D)
    - OK Harris Advertisement Postcards, 1974-1977 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 170.E)
    - OK Harris Advertisement Postcards, 1977-2012 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 170.F)
  - Subseries XIX.3. O.K. Harris exhibition prints and posters
    Consists of a variety of prints and posters that were exhibited and relate to exhibits held at O.K. Harris.
    - Radical Realism I (6 prints) (Oversize Flat File, Folder 198)
      Includes 6 signed and numbered lithographed prints from the exhibition Radical Realism I presented to O.K. Harris by the Mother Lode Editions and Hundred Acres Gallery. The names of the artists and their prints are as follows: John Clem Clarke, Bacchanal; Richard Estes, Cafeteria; Ralph Goings, Paul's Corner; Richard McClean, Native Dancer; Malcolm Morley, Rhine Chataeu; and John Salt, Arrested Vehicle in Red Seats.
    - Baeder, John (3 prints) (Oversize Flat File, Folder 199)
      Includes 3 prints by John Baeder. The names of these prints are as follows: Big Boy Bop (1985) signed; Scotts's Brige Diner (1975); Lan Ting NYC signed.
    - Bechtle, Robert (1 print) (Oversize Flat File, Folder 199)
      Includes 1 signed untitled print by John Baeder
    - Cone, Davis (3 prints) (Oversize Flat File, Folder 200)
      Includes 3 signed prints by Davis Cone. The names of these prints are as follows: Criterion Center (1988); Greenwich; and Orleans
    - Kacere, John (3 prints) (Oversize Flat File, Folder 200)
      Includes 3 prints by John Kacere. The names of these prints are as follows: White Satin Rear View (1973), signed; Greta (1982); Greta (1982), poster.
    - Goings, Ralph (6 prints) (Oversize Flat File, Folder 201)
      Includes 6 prints by Ralph Goings. The names of these prints are as follows: Still Life With Creamer (1985); Hot Sauce, signed; Ralph's Diner; Cream Pie; Kentucky Fried Chicken, signed; and Catsup.
    - McClean, Richard (2 prints) (Oversize Flat File, Folder 202)
      Includes 2 prints by Richard McClean. The names of these prints are as follows: Spring Doe; Man Holding Reins of White Horse.
    - Salt, John (4 prints) (Oversize Flat File, Folder 202)
      Includes 4 prints by Davis Cone. The names of these prints are as follows: Blue Car/Red Car Upper Right; White Pontiac, signed; Blue Car Interior, signed; and Galerie Delta Rotterdam (1981), poster.
    - Variety of posters relating to O.K. Harris exhibitions (Oversize Flat File, Folder 203)
      Includes a variety of posters and prints from various exhibitions. The names of the artist and their prints are as follows: Oscar Lakeman; Greg Constantine (1987), poster; Ivan C. Karp, photographs from the 40s and 50s, poster; Ivan C, Karp, The Face of Contemporary Art: A Celebration of 40 Years of Fine Arts Dealership, poster; John Fawcett, Walt Disney's Comics and Stories, signed; John Fawcett, Drawings and Comic Books, signed; Keung Szeto (1988), Hong Kong Institute for Promotion of Chinese Culture, poster; H.N. Han, signed; Jonathan Janson, Oz (1990); Duane Hanson, Randers Kunstmuseum: Amerikanske Realister, poster.